<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rebellious city destroyed being an anniversary sermon in memory of the dreadful fire of London, on the second day of September, 1666, preached at St. Olave's Hart-Street, London, September the second, 1682 / by William Wray ...</title>
            <author>Wray, William, 1650?-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67145</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8957</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11983685</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11983685</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51921</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67145)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51921)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 523:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rebellious city destroyed being an anniversary sermon in memory of the dreadful fire of London, on the second day of September, 1666, preached at St. Olave's Hart-Street, London, September the second, 1682 / by William Wray ...</title>
                  <author>Wray, William, 1650?-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in University of Pennsylvania Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ezra IV, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  Fire, 1666 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51921:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51921:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Rebellious City Deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being an Anniverſary SERMON In Memory of the Dreadful Fire OF LONDON, On the Second Day of <hi>September,</hi> 1666.</p>
            <p>Preached At St. <hi>Olave</hi>'s <hi>Hart-Street, London, Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> the Second, 1682.</p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM WRAY,</hi> M. A. Chaplain to the Right Honourable <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkley,</hi> Baron of <hi>Stratton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the Biſhops Head in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:51921:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51921:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached <hi>September</hi> 2. 1682.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>EZRA IV. 15.</bibl>
               <q>—<hi>So ſhalt thou find in the Book of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, and know that this City is a Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous City, and hurtful unto Kings and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, and that they have moved Sedition within the ſame of old time: for which cauſe was this City deſtroyed.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Pious deſign of your preſent <hi>Meeting</hi> is, to teſtifie unto God and the World, what <hi>Humiliation,</hi> his ſevere Judgment upon this <hi>City</hi> (yet freſh in your <hi>Thoughts,</hi> and yet felt in many of your <hi>Fortunes</hi>) hath begot in you. That it ill behooves you now to <hi>diſſemble,</hi> or proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inſiſt upon <hi>Self-juſtification.</hi> God has
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51921:3"/> ſignally manifeſted his <hi>Diſpleaſure:</hi> and does not uſe to ſcatter ſuch Plagues as <hi>theſe</hi> at <hi>random,</hi> nor ſuffer his Vengeance to fall ſo heavy and Epidemically, but where he has been out of meaſure <hi>provok'd.</hi> Indeed <hi>private</hi> Calamities often light upon <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> Men for other Reaſons; and are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways intended for the Puniſhment of <hi>Sin,</hi> neither are they infallible Symptoms of the Wrath of God againſt thoſe that are thus viſited. But where a <hi>City,</hi> a <hi>Metropolis,</hi> and in that a whole <hi>Nation</hi> is concern'd, and where the Judgment is ſo dreadfully <hi>remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi> ſo full of <hi>Terror</hi> and <hi>Amazement</hi> as that of <hi>this Day;</hi> we muſt not think that <hi>Providence</hi> plays at <hi>ſmall-games,</hi> and onely <hi>recreates</hi> it ſelf with theſe <hi>ſportive</hi> Tragedies, deſigning nothing worſe than its own <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion:</hi> No, God does not uſe ſo <hi>ſeriouſly</hi> to <hi>Trifle,</hi> nor <hi>Jeſt</hi> with Nations when he <hi>deſtroys</hi> them. Such ſignal Judgments are ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dent Signs that he is <hi>ſolemnly Angry</hi> and in <hi>good earneſt.</hi> That we do but fondly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude our own Conſciences, and aggravate the Provocation, by wipeing our Mouths and pleading <hi>Innocence.</hi> This is plainly to give his Vengeance the <hi>Lie,</hi> and to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51921:3"/> that woful Truth, which he knows bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than <hi>our ſelves.</hi> 'Tis as vain to diſſemble our Guilt to the <hi>World</hi> alſo. For God hath made us <hi>Notorious</hi> to all that are round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us: and <hi>they</hi> muſt be very dull and inadvertent, that do not <hi>obſerve</hi> our Shame, with a very diſtinct and Judicious <hi>Notice;</hi> and the City in <hi>Flames,</hi> has <hi>Beacon'd</hi> and Blaz'd it abroad to the whole World. And how ſhall we Juſtifie our ſelves before <hi>Men,</hi> whom <hi>God</hi> has ſo <hi>publickly</hi> and <hi>formally</hi> Condemned! <hi>If we ſay that we have no Sin,</hi> they may juſtly alledg his Judgments to our Faces, that <hi>there is no Truth in us:</hi> an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of more undoubted Credit, than any that we can Forge in our own Defence; for the Matter is come to this Iſſue, whether it be Right to hearken unto <hi>God</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us therefore deal ſincerely with God, the World, and our own Conſciences; and Ingenuouſly <hi>confeſs,</hi> and ſoberly <hi>Repent</hi> thoſe <hi>manifeſt</hi> Sins which we cannot <hi>hide:</hi> and not Ridicule the Divine Juſtice with a <hi>Mock-faſt;</hi> and ſo our Incenſe become as great an <hi>Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination,</hi> as any of thoſe <hi>Evils</hi> for which we ſuffer. Which that you may the better do, I ſhall endeavor to direct your Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51921:4"/> in the way of a <hi>Self-diſcovery,</hi> by lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before you the <hi>groſſeſt</hi> of thoſe Sins that we of this City and Nation have been moſt <hi>Emphatically</hi> guilty of, and which God hath infinite Reaſon to be Angry at. And doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thoſe of the Text are the very <hi>Rubrick,</hi> and ſtand in the front of the <hi>Kalendar.</hi> Theſe are they for which our Infamous Names are deſervedly <hi>Poſted,</hi> for which the World <hi>hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> at us, and all the <hi>Babyloniſh Samaritans</hi> at home and abroad upbraid us ſaying, This, this is the <hi>Rebellious City, and hurtful unto Kings, for which cauſe this City was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In handling of which words, we will Firſt, Give you an account of the Story to which they relate, and</p>
            <p>Secondly, See how far it is applicable to the preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>For the Hiſtory we muſt look back, at<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.</note> the leaſt, as far as the Reign of <hi>Hoſhea, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboams</hi> Succeſſor over the ten revolted Tribes which dwelt in <hi>Samaria:</hi> whoſe Dominions <hi>Shalmeneſer</hi> the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> invaded, and made the Land Tributary. But they neglected to pay the <hi>Annual Duty,</hi> and maintain'd a correſpondence with the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51921:4"/> the Iſraelites in all their Diſtreſſes were too apt to do. Which Affront <hi>Shalmeneſer</hi> ſo highly reſented, that he ſent his Forces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into <hi>Samaria,</hi> took <hi>Hoſhea</hi> Priſoner, and at three years end poſſeſt himſelf of all the Cities, and carried the Inhabitants Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive into his own Land: Into whoſe <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Dwellings,</hi> he tranſplanted ſome of his own Country-men, and <hi>they poſſeſt Samaria</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe 14.</note> 
               <hi>and dwelt in the Cities thereof.</hi> But theſe <hi>Babilonians</hi> did not change their <hi>Religion</hi> with their <hi>Climate,</hi> neither Worſhipped they the <hi>true</hi> God, but ſerved the Abominations of their Fathers, and walked in all the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious</hi> ways they had been ſeverally brought up in. For which Cauſe God let<note place="margin">verſ. 24.</note> looſe the wild Beaſts of the Field upon them, and many of them were deſtroy'd by <hi>Lions.</hi> By this means they were brought to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand<note place="margin">verſe 25.</note> their <hi>Errour;</hi> and ſent to acquaint the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> what had befallen them, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>they knew not the manner of the God of the Land.</hi> Hereupon the King ſent them a <hi>Prieſt</hi> from among thoſe of the Captivity, to inſtruct them in the <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> of the <hi>true</hi> God. But ſo ſtrong and invincible were the the Prejudices of their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51921:5"/> Education, that the true Religion found but cold Entertainment among them: and though the Intereſts of <hi>ſelf-preſervation</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſably neceſſitated them to <hi>profeſs</hi> it; yet all that God could by his Judgments <hi>force,</hi> or the Prieſt <hi>perſwade</hi> them to, was onely to admit <hi>Him</hi> among their other Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to <hi>make One</hi> in their heathen Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue. <hi>For they feared the Lord, and ſerved</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe 33.</note> 
               <hi>their own Gods, after the manner of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> from whence they came. And by this medly of Religion they were ſeperated and diſtinguiſh'd from them of the Jewiſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, unto the very time of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours coming into the World, and from thence forward till the <hi>final Diſperſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> having thus got Footing in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and open'd the way into a more entire <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> made their next Attempts upon <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> But good King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> by his own perſonal <hi>Integrity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.</note> and his <hi>Zeal</hi> for Gods Glory and the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſts of Religion, kept off the ſtroke all the time of his own Reign. But when the Date of his Life was out, <hi>Piety</hi> died and was Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with him: And <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> his Son con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded the <hi>Reformation</hi> his Father had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51921:5"/> made, revived all the ruined Monuments of<note place="margin">chap. 21.</note> Idolatry, rear'd up Alters for <hi>Baal,</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped all the Hoſt of Heaven, brought the Abomination even into the <hi>Holy Place,</hi> and ſet up a graven Image in the Houſe of the Lord. Thus Religion was laid waſt, and a <hi>Babel</hi> of ſuperſtition built upon its ruins. Nay, to fill up the Meaſure of <hi>Impieties,</hi> he practis'd <hi>Witchcraft,</hi> and kept a familiar Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. verſe 6.</note> with <hi>Devils.</hi> And no wonder if <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs</hi> go hand in hand no wonder if <hi>they</hi> have no regard to the good of <hi>Men,</hi> that have not the Fear of <hi>God</hi> before their eyes. Blood is the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Cement of every Religion, that ſtands beſide the Foundation of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and force the ſupport of that <hi>disjoynted</hi> Cauſe that would otherwiſe tumble and be its own confuſion. To this <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> had Recourſe, ſuſpecting that his <hi>bad Divinity</hi> would never propagate and ſtand, but by the help of <hi>cruel Politicks,</hi> (Arguments as wicked as the Cauſe.) And accordingly you read, that <hi>he ſhed innocent Blood very much,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. 16.</note> 
               <hi>till he had filled</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>from one end to the other.</hi> And this was indeed the grand pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation that incenſed the Divine Juſtice ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51921:6"/> irreconcileably, againſt that <hi>Place</hi> and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Manaſſeh</hi>'s wicked Reign was the ground of all thoſe Prophetick Threats,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34. 23. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. 10.</note> that open'd the Mouths of <hi>Huldah</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheteſs, of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah.</hi> And for this Cauſe was <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> himſelf, the firſt of all the Men of <hi>Judah,</hi> delivered into the<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32. 11.</note> hands of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> as an earneſt of the approaching <hi>Captivity.</hi> And from this time forward the <hi>Babylonians</hi> every day got Ground upon them; bating that little <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpit</hi> in <hi>Joſiahs</hi> time, in the latter end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of<note place="margin">chap 35. verſe 20.</note> the <hi>Egyptians</hi> helped to do the work for them. After this <hi>Nebuchadnezzer</hi> retook the<note place="margin">chap. 36. verſe 5.</note> Cauſe into his own hands, ſubdued <hi>Jehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kim,</hi> who for three years held the Crown <hi>in Capite</hi> of the Conquerour; but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting, became acceſſary to his own <hi>Fall. Jehoiachin</hi> his Son had ſcarce Reigned three<note place="margin">verſe 9.</note> Months, when his City was Beſeiged, his Perſon ſeized on, his Relations, Officers of State, Guards and Forces, nay all the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> taken; to the number of ten thouſand Men: ſo that none remained but the <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Refuſe</hi> of the Land, that ſeem'd <hi>beneath</hi> the Enemies Diſpleaſure, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver whom <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> made <hi>Zedekiah</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe 11.</note>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51921:6"/> King. But he Rebelled againſt his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, and called in the <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> Which Act of <hi>Confederacy</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> ſo enraged the Enemy, that, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſperſt their Forces and entred the City, they put the Inhabitants to the <hi>Sword,</hi> half dead before with <hi>Famine</hi> and <hi>Peſtilence.</hi> Neither the gray Hairs of the <hi>Aged,</hi> nor the<note place="margin">verſe 17.</note> promiſing hopes of <hi>Youth,</hi> nor the Charms of <hi>Virginity,</hi> nor the Innocent Oratory of <hi>Infant Tenderneſs,</hi> could divert the Courſe of their <hi>impartial</hi> Fury: All places <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Prophane</hi> were alike to them, and the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> it ſelf became a <hi>Tophet</hi> and Place of Execution. And thoſe poor Remains that eſcaped the Fury of the Sword, were carried away to <hi>Babylon,</hi> there to <hi>partake</hi> in the Captivity of their <hi>Brethren,</hi> and <hi>bewail</hi> their <hi>Own.</hi> Then was the Temple Sacked, the Exchequer Plundered, and all the Seats of the Nobility Spoiled and Pillaged: And having poſſeſt themſelves of all the porta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Treaſure of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they brake down the Wall ſet fire of the Temple, and left all her goodly Palaces in Flames.</p>
            <p>In this State of Captivity the <hi>Jews</hi> remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed till the <hi>ſeventy years</hi> of <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s Propheſy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51921:7"/> were accompliſhed. When, <hi>Babylon</hi> being ſubjected to the <hi>Perſian</hi> Empire, God put it<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 1. 1.</note> into the Heart of <hi>Cyrus</hi> to ſet his People free, and to rebuild the City and Temple, that the <hi>Caldeans</hi> had deſtroyed. To this end he gave them leave to go up, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored unto them all the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſils</hi> of the Houſe of God, and ordered them to be furniſhed, out of the places where they ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed, with Silver and Gold, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever elſe was neceſſary for the Undertaking. And having now with Joy begun the Work,<note place="margin">chap. 4. 1.</note> the <hi>Samaritans</hi> (of whom I gave you an Account before) ſollicite the <hi>Heads</hi> of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> that <hi>they</hi> might be joined with them in the Building of the Temple: pretending that they Worſhipped the <hi>ſame</hi> God, and Profeſt the <hi>ſame</hi> Religion which the <hi>Jews</hi> did. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>So our Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries plead for compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, do we not own Chriſt, his Goſpel, the ſame points of Faith, the ſame Acts of Worſhip, ſee Dr.</hi> Owen Plea <hi>for Non-Con.</hi> p. 21. verſe 4.</note> But the <hi>Fathers</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> well knowing that ſuch a <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> would endanger the <hi>Purity</hi> of Religion, and the peace of the Church, utterly reject the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, and tell them flatly, that they neither had, nor ſhould have, any thing to do with them in Building a Houſe to their God; but that they would do it <hi>Themſelves,</hi> as King <hi>Cyrus</hi> had commanded them. This
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51921:7"/> Anſwer ſo netled the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> that they reſolved, (if it were poſſible,) to hinder, what they could not be admitted to have a hand in: To which end they had always ſome States-man or other <hi>in Fee,</hi> to perſwade the<note place="margin">verſe 5. 6. 7.</note> King to revoke his Grant, and countermand what he had Decreed. At length, <hi>Cyrus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſonally engaged abroad in Forreign Enterprizes, and in the mean time, conſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Adminiſtration of the Government to his Son <hi>Cambyſes,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Ahaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſeph. <hi>de Antiqu. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daic.</hi> l. 11. c. 3 Tirin. <hi>in loc &amp; Alii.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Artaxerxes;</hi> the <hi>Samaritans</hi> looked upon this as a fit Juncture to work their Deſigns in: Wherefore pretending them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves mightily concerned for the Honour<note place="margin">verſe 14.</note> and Peace of the Government, they ſend a Letter to the Vice King, to let him know of what dangerous Conſequence the Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> might be; that the Jews were a <hi>factious</hi> &amp; <hi>unquiet</hi> People, and if once their Hands were ſtrengthened, and their City Fortified, they would in all likelihood Revolt, and refuſe to pay <hi>Toll, and Tribute, and Cuſtome;</hi> and by this means the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of the Crown would be impared: for the Probability and Truth whereof, they refer him to the ancient Chronicles, where
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51921:8"/> he ſhould find <hi>that this City had been a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious City, and hurtful unto Kings,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Which Accuſation, though <hi>ſpiteful</hi> and <hi>invidious,</hi> was not altogether <hi>falſe:</hi> For upon Enquiry, <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> found it was as they had ſaid; that the City had formerly <hi>made Inſurrection againſt Kings, and that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 19.</note> 
               <hi>and Sedition had been made therein.</hi> So that all the Untruth, if there be any, muſt lie in the <hi>Miſapplication: For which Cauſe this City was deſtroyed:</hi> when indeed, their Deſtruction was the Execution of God's Sentence upon the Sins of <hi>Manaſſeh;</hi> but we do not find, that Sedition or Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion are any where reckoned in that Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue. But notwithſtanding that this was the <hi>Original</hi> Cauſe of God's <hi>diſpleaſure,</hi> yet Sedition and Rebellion were in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the <hi>proximate</hi> Cauſe of its Execution. For the Revolt of <hi>Jehoiakin</hi> and <hi>Zedekiah</hi> haſtened their Ruine, and effectually brought the final Judgment upon them. They were a <hi>Conquered</hi> People, and by the Law of Nations bound to undergo that Yoke which their Sins had put about their Necks. As for <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> he was <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzars</hi> own Creature, and of <hi>his</hi> preferring:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51921:8"/> he had alſo taken a ſolemn Oath of <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> and depoſited, his Faith before God, as a Pledg of his Loyalty and Obedience: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, he had an expreſs <hi>Command</hi> from God by the Mouth of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Solemnly back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Sanctions of Promiſes and Threats, to put his <hi>Neck under the Yoke of</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 27. 12.</note> 
               <hi>the King of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and to ſerve him and his People,</hi> which (if he did he ſhould <hi>Live;</hi> but if not, <hi>He</hi> and <hi>His</hi> ſhould <hi>Die,</hi> by the <hi>Famine,</hi> by the <hi>Sword,</hi> and by the <hi>Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence;</hi>) but he ſtiffened his Neck and would<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. 13.</note> not hearken, but Conſpired with the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> and Raiſed Sedition and Rebellion. Now, whether the Text refers to theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, (as probably it does) or to any other, I diſpute not; but this is certain that for <hi>this Cauſe,</hi> among others, <hi>the City was deſtroyed.</hi> This is the Story, let us now proceed to the Application.</p>
            <p>Our Judgments are not much unlike to Theirs: only God hath, in Mercy, hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to abated us the <hi>Famine,</hi> which we have no leſs deſerved then They. But we have been <hi>Blooded</hi> till our Veins were almoſt dry. We have been in <hi>Captivity,</hi> and our Lives and Liberties ſold into the Hands of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51921:9"/> and Uſurpers. We have been <hi>Plagued</hi> with a Witneſs, and have ſeen Death march with his Armies through our Streets a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Thouſand ſtrong. And as this was the immediate Forerunner of <hi>Jeruſalem's</hi> Deſolation; ſo no ſooner were our <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> returned to their Houſes, from whence the <hi>deſtroying Angel</hi> had driven them, but the <hi>Fire</hi> conſumed their Dwellings, and the ſame wet Eyes, that pay'd the laſt Tribute at the Graves of their <hi>Relations</hi> and <hi>Friends,</hi> were ſet afloat afreſh to bewail the City it ſelf Buried in its own Duſt; The Shops of Trade, the Halls of Companies, the Royal Burſe of Merchants, the Habitations of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, the Seats of Judgment, the Temples of God, being all crumbled into Aſhes, and ſcarce <hi>one ſtone left upon another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And dare we ſtill Juſtifie our ſelves, and ſay we are Innocent, and Plagued for <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing?</hi> Did God thus viſit his <hi>own</hi> People for their <hi>Sins,</hi> and ſhall we that have had the very ſame Sentence Executed upon us, plead <hi>Not Guilty?</hi> Theſe things are <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our Example:</hi> And I think we have Copied them out to <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> and are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Antitype</hi> of their <hi>Plagnes</hi> and <hi>Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:51921:9"/>
            <p>The Sins of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> were <hi>Idolatry; Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery</hi> and <hi>Bloodſhed.</hi> The <hi>Firſt</hi> of theſe (by the Help of God) we have long ſince Rooted out; and our <hi>immoderate Fear</hi> of it, is one of the greateſt Superſtitions that now remain among us: But yet our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples have been no leſs defiled, than theirs at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> The Sanctuary hath been the Priſon of the Loyal and Innocent; our Altars have been Debauched with Rioting and Drunkenneſs; our Pulpits the Mint of Blaſphemy, Hereſie and Sedition; The Houſe of God a Den of Thieves, a Slaughter-Houſe of Murder, a Stable of Horſes. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filements,</hi> that <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> would, perhaps, have Trembled at, and that none but <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians,</hi> and ſuch as dare <hi>Fire</hi> a Temple, durſt have been Guilty of. And that <hi>Ours</hi> eſcaped it <hi>Then,</hi> was more of God's Mercy, than any Sence of Religion on the <hi>Propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> part.</p>
            <p>The next Sin of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> that the Spirit<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. 6.</note> of God hath put a Mark upon, is <hi>Sorcery;</hi> and I doubt not but we may Match it with a <hi>Parallel.</hi> For what do you call <hi>inſpired Lights, Viſions, Revelations, Daunings, Breathings,</hi> and the like Familiar <hi>Incomes</hi> of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51921:10"/> a <hi>Private Spirit?</hi> which, if they be not <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Witchcraft,</hi> no ſober Man knows how to define. What is, I ſay, the <hi>Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſm</hi> of theſe latter Ages, but the <hi>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi> of a Satanical Spirit with Mens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Phancies, whereby the Devil hath made a better Market of his Sophiſticated Impoſtures, among us of this Nation, than ever he did in the World before? And what is that Barbarous <hi>Cant</hi> and <hi>Phraſeology,</hi> that we have been ſo long cheated with, (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Notion of <hi>Powerful Preaching,</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Raptures,</hi> the Sence whereof is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Myſterious,</hi> or <hi>None;</hi>) but meer <hi>Charms</hi> and <hi>Exorciſms,</hi> to bewitch Vulgar Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and <hi>Spells</hi> to poſſeſs and lead their Affections Captive.</p>
            <p>The laſt of <hi>Manaſſeh's noted</hi> Sins is <hi>Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</hi> He Murdered his own Subjects, and ſo had the pretence of an abuſed <hi>Power.</hi> But we, without all Power, and againſt all, but what we <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped,</hi> Murdered thoſe, whoſe Lives were as much their own as <hi>ours,</hi> and more: Our <hi>Fellow-ſubjects,</hi> our <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Acquaintance,</hi> our <hi>Brethren</hi> and <hi>Fathers,</hi> our <hi>Maſters</hi> and <hi>Governours,</hi> our <hi>Prieſts,</hi> our <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> our <hi>King,</hi> and defiled the Land with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51921:10"/> its <hi>beſt</hi> and <hi>vital</hi> Blood. And what more could <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> do, or wherein was his ſin of Blood-ſhed (<hi>which the Lord would not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>)<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 24. 4.</note> greater than ours?</p>
            <p>And now let us ſee what we have to plead to the <hi>Samaritans</hi> Charge; Nay, rather let us <hi>confeſs</hi> the Fact, and ſay as They and all the World do; that we are a <hi>Rebellious City, and hurtful unto Kings.</hi> For our Guilt is too <hi>manifeſt</hi> to be hid, and of too deep a Grain, to be blanched by Pleas and Excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Sedition and Rebellion are the Articles of the Indictment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sedition;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that is either <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> or <hi>Laic.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hales <hi>of Schiſm.</hi> D. 1.</note> For there is no great difference between <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> and <hi>Schiſm;</hi> but that Cuſtom hath diſtinguiſhed them, appropriating <hi>One</hi> to a Civil, and the <hi>Other</hi> to an Eccleſiaſtical ſence. And for <hi>Church-ſedition:</hi> What Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple profeſſing one <hi>common Faith,</hi> were ever more miſerably divided then <hi>We</hi> have been? In how many ſhapes have we dreſt up Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and called it by ſo many <hi>Names,</hi> till our Wits were puzled to find out Names <hi>enough</hi> to call it by? We had ingroſſed all the Hereſies of former Ages, and wracked
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51921:11"/> our Inventions, to Coin a Multitude more, that the World never heard of till <hi>Then:</hi> And every one of <hi>theſe,</hi> Conſtituted a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of a diſtinct Denomination from all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind beſide. That the whole Nation was, almoſt, <hi>unchurched;</hi> and nothing in the World, but a Pack of Schiſmaticks, ſhuff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led together without any <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> or <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haerence.</hi> The Body of Chriſt was rended Piece-meal; and the divided Members, like Bones in a <hi>Charnel houſe,</hi> lay <hi>unmatched;</hi> and no man could tell how they <hi>related.</hi> Every Man was a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> Every Man a <hi>Saint;</hi> (and almoſt every man a Church too,) but we were Chriſtians and Saints at <hi>large,</hi> and <hi>Indefinitely;</hi> it being Impoſſible to find out wherein our Relation to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Communion of Saints</hi> Conſiſted; or how we belonged to the Common Head, by any Joint Order, and Connexion of the Parts unto one another.</p>
            <p>This Breach of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in Religion, eaſily divided our <hi>Affections;</hi> and when once we ceaſed to be <hi>Brethren,</hi> the Gap ſoon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to ſuch a Diſtance; that in fine we were not <hi>Friends. All</hi> were extreme fond of their own Perſwaſions; Impatient to hear their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51921:11"/> Opinions ſlighted; zealous to prefer their particular Conceits; and Imoderately am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, to ſee their Judgments <hi>Enthroned;</hi> and that the Pragmatick Votes of their own <hi>private</hi> Fancies, might paſs into <hi>publick Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,</hi> and become the <hi>Eſtabliſhed, Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Forms</hi> of Religion to the whole Church and Nation.</p>
            <p>And thus from our differences in <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> aroſe <hi>Sedition</hi> in the <hi>State:</hi> Here was the firſt Ground of the Quarrellaid: From theſe unhappy Beginnings, we proceeded to hate, and revile, and proſeeute one another, with the utmoſt Spight and Rancour. At the firſt we demurely pretended, that we ſought onely the <hi>Liberty</hi> of our own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, but afterward nothing would ſerve us leſs, than the <hi>ſovereignty</hi> over other Mens: And they that refuſed to allow us <hi>this,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd themſelves our Enemies in <hi>that</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial; (the Government it ſelf not excepted) and as ſuch we proceeded againſt them; Firſt with bitter Words, and then with downright Blows: and by theſe Degrees <hi>Sedition</hi> advanced to an <hi>Open</hi> and <hi>unnatural</hi> Rebellion.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Rebellion</hi> that had no tollerable Pretence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51921:12"/> to Juſtify it. A Rebellion moſt unreaſonably charg'd upon the Score of Religion; which in the <hi>General</hi> does no where countenance it, and for that of this Church in <hi>particular,</hi> it neither <hi>needed</hi> nor <hi>deſerved</hi> it. For it was Reformed allready, as far as Reformation was <hi>neceſſary,</hi> and almoſt <hi>tollerable,</hi> that is, to its <hi>Primative</hi> Purity: and wanted nothing, ſo much, towards it's due Perfection, as the <hi>Conformity</hi> of thoſe, that exclaim'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. And the Conſcientious Profeſſion and Practice of it, might have made us <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py</hi> in <hi>this</hi> World and in the next; if it be in the Power of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelf to make us ſo. Religion was as <hi>entire,</hi> as Chriſt and his Apoſtles left it; our Articles of Faith were neither <hi>more</hi> nor <hi>leſs,</hi> than theirs; and our Rules of Life, the <hi>ſame.</hi> And for thoſe Ceremonies that made all the Noiſe, what were they, but ſuch decent Uſeages, as were recommended to us, by the beſt of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> for the firſt four Hundred years: who look'd upon them as the <hi>Ornaments</hi> of Religious Worſhip; and <hi>lived</hi> and <hi>died</hi> in the Uſe of them. That if they were ſuch <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian</hi> Prejudices to Religion, and the Salvation of Men, as has been pretended;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51921:12"/> We muſt Judge very <hi>hardly</hi> of thoſe bleſſed Saints and Martyrs: that they are either on this ſide Heaven, or that they made but very narrow Eſcapes thither. But if Religion had been out of <hi>repair,</hi> how <hi>unfit</hi> a Rebellion was to <hi>mend</hi> it, I hope by this time we are all convinced.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Rebellion,</hi> as <hi>unreaſonable</hi> on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Government,</hi> as of <hi>Religion:</hi> And more <hi>unreaſonable</hi> it could not be For as <hi>Monarchy</hi> is the <hi>beſt</hi> of all Governments, ſo is <hi>Ours</hi> the <hi>beſt</hi> of the <hi>ſort.</hi> A <hi>Government</hi> Eſtabliſhed by <hi>wholſome</hi> Laws; that gives to every man as much Right and Liberty, as <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Modeſty</hi> can crave. <hi>Laws,</hi> that have abated the Royalties of the <hi>Crown,</hi> for the <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Eaſment</hi> of the People. <hi>Laws,</hi> of our own <hi>Chooſing,</hi> and ſuch as our <hi>ſelves</hi> have voted for; that no man can Suffer by them, but upon his own <hi>Verdict.</hi> That a <hi>better</hi> Government we cannot have, nor an <hi>Eaſier;</hi> and they that do not think ſo, I am affraid, do, for their <hi>own Sakes,</hi> wiſh that there might be <hi>None.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of this ſo <hi>moderate</hi> and <hi>kindly</hi> Government, was then in the Hands of a <hi>Monarch</hi> ſo <hi>Piouſly Devout,</hi> ſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51921:13"/> 
               <hi>Morally Juſt,</hi> ſo <hi>Chriſtianly Good;</hi> ſo every way <hi>unfit</hi> to fix a <hi>Rebellion</hi> upon; that we could never have <hi>timed</hi> it ſo unhappily, to our own Eternal ſhame, from the firſt <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch</hi> that ever ſwey'd the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Scepter until now.</p>
            <p>But as theſe Conſiderations prevailed not to ſilence the <hi>Seditious</hi> Clamours, and tie down the Hands of a <hi>Rebellious</hi> People; ſo, neither did they abate one Grain of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, in carrying on the <hi>Bloody</hi> Work. For their Fury and Spight was all one, as if the <hi>Grand Sultan,</hi> or an Army of <hi>Bears</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> had invaded them; and as if He they fought with, had neither been their <hi>King,</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> nor a <hi>Man:</hi> Refuſing all Treaty but what they <hi>knew,</hi> and were <hi>reſolved</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand, ſhould come to naught. And when they had Caught the Prey they Hunted, in defiance to all <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane</hi> Laws, to that <hi>Natural</hi> Allegiance that Subjects owe their Prince, to their own Solemn <hi>Vows</hi> and <hi>Proteſtations</hi> (which they had only uſed as <hi>Baits</hi> to betray him) they <hi>un-king'd,</hi> un-man'd, and Barbarouſly <hi>Murdered</hi> him; and made no more on't, than if they had <hi>Cut off a Dogs Neck.</hi> All the <hi>Formality</hi> of the thing, being
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51921:13"/> more a matter of <hi>Triumph,</hi> than <hi>Reſpect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Look into your <hi>Records,</hi> Look, if you can for <hi>Shame;</hi> and ſee, if <hi>this City,</hi> be not a <hi>Rebellious</hi> City, and <hi>Hurtful unto Kings? This City,</hi> I ſay, that Influences all the Nation: And whoſe Example, whether <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil,</hi> is a <hi>Preſident</hi> to the whole Kingdom, and Governs it as a Law. In <hi>theſe</hi> Kennels, did the Generation of <hi>Sects and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> Breed. <hi>Here,</hi> where <hi>Schiſms</hi> brought forth and Encouraged. <hi>Here,</hi> was <hi>Faction</hi> Preached, and attended to, with an <hi>Eager</hi> Joy. <hi>Here,</hi> were Seditious <hi>Libells</hi> Penn'd, and Scattered about the Streets. <hi>Here,</hi> Rebels Club'd into <hi>Confederaces,</hi> and model'd <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Aſſociation. This,</hi> was the <hi>Stay</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence</hi> of the Projecting Party. <hi>This,</hi> was the <hi>Refuge</hi> of Traytors, Firſt; and after that<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Five Members firſt ſhelter'd here, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried through the Streets. in Triumph.</hi>
               </note> their <hi>Theatre.</hi> From <hi>Hence,</hi> were Inſolent <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions</hi> prefer'd; and the Government Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited againſt it ſelf, with <hi>Vexatious</hi> Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities. From <hi>Hence,</hi> was the whole Nation <hi>Alarum'd,</hi> and put into a <hi>Fright;</hi> by their Mid-night Out-cries, and unſeaſonable <hi>Doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> their Gaurds and Watches. From <hi>Hence,</hi> was the Royal Palace, more than once, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted, by an <hi>Armed Rabble.</hi> Here, the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51921:14"/> Common <hi>Fund</hi> was chiefly Stock'd, for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on the Deſign; and <hi>they,</hi> that begrudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>Mite</hi> to the <hi>Loan,</hi> could freely offer <hi>Hundreds,</hi> to the <hi>Publick Faith;</hi> and never Boggle at that <hi>Bugbear</hi> Objection of being <hi>Arbitrary.</hi> Finally, <hi>here</hi> were Armies raiſed, Magazines furniſhed, and nothing was wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the City's Part, that their <hi>Zealous Spirits,</hi> their outſtretched <hi>Hands,</hi> or their unchriſtian <hi>Bounty</hi> could do, to promote and further the <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, what ſhould make us afraid to ſay, <hi>that for this Cauſe, this City was deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Schiſm, Sedition,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally weigh'd with the former Circumſtances, are ſuch <hi>aggravating</hi> Sins; that certainly we needed no <hi>additional</hi> Guilt to ruin us.</p>
            <p>And it is no <hi>new thing,</hi> for <hi>ſuch</hi> Sins, to be <hi>ſo</hi> puniſhed. Thus God avenged himſelf, upon the Rebellious Schiſmaticks of old; the firſt of that Denomination: <hi>There came out a</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. 35.</note> 
               <hi>Fire from the Lord, and conſumed them.</hi> And as if it had been their <hi>peculiar</hi> Right and Portion, the Diſciples <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> ask our Saviour, if he would not that <hi>they ſhould</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 9. 54.</note> 
               <hi>command Fire from Heaven, to conſume the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans?</hi> Thoſe obſtinate Seperatiſts, from
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51921:14"/> the Jewiſh Church; who refuſed common Hoſpitality to any one, that did but look <hi>Jeruſalem-ward.</hi> And this Demand of <hi>Theirs,</hi> was grounded upon a like Inſtance. For ſo had <hi>Elijah</hi> the Prophet, deſtroyed a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Schiſmaticks, <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Proſelites in <hi>Samaria.</hi> And that our <hi>Saviour</hi> refuſed to<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.</note> do ſo too, was more upon the account of that <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Loving-kindneſs,</hi> which he was ſo <hi>eminent</hi> for himſelf, and by his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Doctrine, recommended to his <hi>Church;</hi> than either the <hi>Merit</hi> of the <hi>Men</hi> or their <hi>Cauſe.</hi> And though Chriſtianity al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows not, that perſons ſhould be proceeded againſt, by <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggot,</hi> upon a <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> account <hi>in Foro Humano;</hi> Yet this is no A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brigement of the Divine Authority, but that he may ſtill thus Viſit us for our Schiſms, when he pleaſes. Once more: That Laſt <hi>irraparable</hi> Deſtruction, which cauſed <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> to be no more; was every way, the conſequence of their <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Rebellion.</hi> They rejected their <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and would have none of him <hi>to Reign over them:</hi> But ſerved <hi>Their</hi> King, as we did <hi>Ours.</hi> And this was the <hi>primary</hi> Cauſe, of all their after Miſeries. In leſs than forty years, when the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51921:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> Meaſure of their Iniquity was filled up, and they were <hi>dropping-ripe</hi> for Vengeance; as if it came not faſt enough, they Rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaiuſt<note place="margin">Joſeph. <hi>de Anti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Judaic.</hi> l. 18. c. 2</note> 
               <hi>Ceſtius Florus,</hi> their <hi>deputed</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and ſo brought the Empire about their <hi>Ears:</hi> which never gave them over, till they were totally deſtroyed. And in the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Jud Ib.</hi> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> c. 50.</note> very laſt Siege, by <hi>Titus,</hi> though they were oppreſſed by the Enemy <hi>without,</hi> and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and Plague raged <hi>within</hi> their Walls, they ceaſed not to create <hi>Inteſtine</hi> Factions among themſelves: Three ſeveral Parties, whereof the <hi>Zealots</hi> were One, contending Battle-Royal with one another. And this gave the Enemy an <hi>Advantage,</hi> equal to that of their own <hi>Strength.</hi> At length the City being Storm'd, an accidental <hi>Brand,</hi> ſet Fire o'the <hi>Temple;</hi> which no endeavours could<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> l. 12. c. 10.</note> quench, till both the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Temple</hi> were level'd with the Ground.</p>
            <p>Indeed <hi>this City</hi> hath been Guilty of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other <hi>Popular,</hi> and provoking Sins; that doubtleſs were <hi>Acceſſary</hi> to her Ruin: But then they are for the moſt part, the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous <hi>Off-ſpring</hi> of the former, and begot between Schiſm and Rebellion. <hi>Atheiſm</hi> hath made its Party ſtrong, by our <hi>Diivſions</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:51921:15"/> in the Church. Many have been tempted to be of <hi>no</hi> Religion, becauſe there is ſo much controverſy about the <hi>True. Popery,</hi> that we are ſo willing ſhould bear all the <hi>Blame,</hi> has taken hold of the Advantage: and perſwaded many over to that <hi>ſide,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Babylon,</hi> forſooth, is <hi>a City</hi> more <hi>at <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in it ſelf. Prophaneſs</hi> has enter'd at the ſame <hi>Breach;</hi> and the Service of God hath been miſerably neglected, through the ſuſpenſion of the Laws, in Favour of ſquea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Conſciences: neither hath the Grace of God had its due effect upon the minds of Men, in ſuch a <hi>divided</hi> State: for <hi>that</hi> is ordinarily reſtrained to the Communion of the <hi>Church,</hi> and hath no where engaged to follow <hi>Runnagates,</hi> in all their extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant <hi>Rambles,</hi> and <hi>Flyings-out.</hi> So that Men have been left <hi>Defenceleſs,</hi> both by God and the Law; to the Temptations of the Devil, and the Incentives of their own Luſts: and no marvel then, that they are ſo <hi>Licentious</hi> and <hi>Prophane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that <hi>Rebellion</hi> hath been as good a Friend to Vice, as <hi>Schiſm,</hi> we need not que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. For it is a Sin of that prodigious <hi>Bulk,</hi> that where it enters, it makes an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51921:16"/> into the Conſcience, and leaves an open Paſſage to all the leſſer <hi>Fry,</hi> to enter after it. Beſides, it is a <hi>Propagating</hi> Sin, and <hi>Many</hi> are the natural Iſſue of it. Such as <hi>Fierceneſs, Revenge,</hi> and <hi>Murder,</hi> &amp;c. For they that have been <hi>Fleſh'd</hi> and <hi>Blooded</hi> in an unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral War, and have ſeen Thouſands Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing upon the Spot; are paſt trembling at a ſingle Man's Fall: eſpecially ſuch as have been Murderers by <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed THE <hi>unrighteous</hi> Cauſe. To theſe we may add <hi>Rapine</hi> and <hi>Injuſtice:</hi> for what can come amiſs to thoſe Mens Hands, that have been uſed to Plunder Palaces, Rob Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and Prey upon the ſequeſtred Rights of <hi>Gods Inheritance?</hi> Laſtly, <hi>Curſing</hi> and <hi>Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Whordom</hi> and <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> are no where ſo <hi>aptly</hi> taught as in an Army, the <hi>School</hi> of Debauches. Nor were they ever ſo openly practiſed in this Nation, as they have been ſince that unhappy time. And what elſe could be expected, but that wickedneſs ſhould break in, like a Torrent upon us; when all the Bonds of Reſtraint were broken and every Man left <hi>to do what was Right in his own Eyes?</hi> And now our Sins have taken ſuch hold upon us, that they were not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51921:16"/> to be broken off: Cuſtom has made them <hi>Familiar,</hi> and Familiarity is improved into <hi>Delight;</hi> that we purſue our Luſts with infinite Deſire and <hi>Greedineſs:</hi> not being lyable to the checks of Shame, or the fears of Diſgrace; Becauſe, the worſt of Sins, are now but common Failings, and every Day produces Inſtances of the like kind. And for all <hi>this,</hi> we are unfortunatly Beholden to our <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Rebellion.</hi> So that if this City was deſtroyed upon the account of our Sins; then doubtleſs Schiſm and Rebellion had the Principle and <hi>Leading</hi> hand in the Judgment.</p>
            <p>And now, what will the <hi>Samaritans</hi> ſay to theſe things? why, they will call us Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels to our <hi>Teeth,</hi> and <hi>Laugh</hi> at the Miſery and Shame, we have brought upon our ſelves. When we tell them of the <hi>Henries</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> or the <hi>Powder-plot</hi> nearer hand; The Tragick Hiſtory of the <hi>Martyr'd Charles,</hi> will Strike us Dumb: For the Children of <hi>Babel</hi> were never guilty of a more bloody Deed: <hi>For which Cauſe this City was deſtroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well But they are only the <hi>Samaritans</hi> that ſay ſo; thoſe <hi>Babylonians</hi> that helped to deſtroy it. Yes, our own Conſciences, if
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51921:17"/> they be ſoundly put to it, will tell us ſo too: and would often have told us ſo er'e this, if we had not ſtifled their Clamours; being loath to aſcribe our Ruine to <hi>that,</hi> which we are ſo ready to do <hi>again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Babylonians,</hi> ſay we, ſet Fire to our Habitations. I ſhould be loath to wrong them, and add the Sin of an uncharitable Cenſure, to thoſe I am called to Repent of <hi>This Day.</hi> But ſuppoſe it were ſo: our Sins, Alas, betrayed the City into their Hands. If we had not loſt our Charter, and forfeited our Right, in the Divine Protection; the Flames <hi>of Hell could not have prevailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</hi> That we may ſay in this Caſe, as our Saviour did to <hi>Pilate</hi> in another. <hi>They</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 19. 11.</note> 
               <hi>could have had no power at all againſt</hi> this place, <hi>had it not been given them from above: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we that delivered it unto them, have the greater Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having diſcovered to you the <hi>true</hi> Cauſe (or what we have too much Reaſon to ſuſpect was ſo) of that <hi>dreadful</hi> Calamity, we are this Day met together to Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and deplore; let me exhort you to a ſerious Repentance of thoſe Sins, that, in all probability, occaſion'd it. For if <hi>they</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape us, we <hi>Faſt,</hi> and keep the Day to no
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51921:17"/> purpoſe. Sedition and Rebellion are ſins of that formidable <hi>Look</hi> and of that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous <hi>Size,</hi> that if <hi>they</hi> do not pain our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and put them in Travel to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; there's little hopes that our <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſized</hi> Immoralities, will beget in us any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe or <hi>Godly ſorrow working Repentance.</hi> If we can carry ſuch a <hi>Load</hi> upon our Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks, our <hi>Leſſer</hi> ſins will be eaſily digeſted: and ſo we <hi>are</hi> but as we <hi>were;</hi> neither <hi>humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> by the Judgment, nor <hi>better'd</hi> by the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity of the Day. I charge none of <hi>you</hi> with Schiſm or Rebellion: but yet I exhort you to Repent of both, For though you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver worſhipped upon Mount <hi>Gerizim;</hi> though your Hands were never ſtaind with Royal-Blood, nor lifted up againſt the Lords Anointed; yet if you do not reſent theſe Sins with a very ſerious Abhorrence, and be not deeply affected with the Guilt of the <hi>Nation;</hi> your Hearts are <hi>tainted;</hi> and you <hi>partake</hi> in the Sins, with thoſe that <hi>Acted</hi> them.</p>
            <p>'Tis too much to be feared, that theſe ſins have ſcarce entr'd our <hi>penitential</hi> Thoughts; or that they have paſſed through them <hi>Raw</hi> and unconcocted; and like <hi>unſavory</hi> Pills,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51921:18"/> or <hi>bitter</hi> Draughts, have been turned off with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Reliſhing.</hi> For our <hi>Diſobedience</hi> to the Government, our unneceſſary <hi>Seperations</hi> from the Church, our <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>Vehemency</hi> againſt <hi>both,</hi> and our <hi>Factions</hi> and <hi>Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> among our ſelves, look ſo unlike any thing of <hi>Humiliation,</hi> that they rather ſpeak us <hi>Proud</hi> both of our Sins and Judgments. And as if it were not time to ſay to the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer</hi> it is <hi>Enough,</hi> we are ſtill ſtirring up the <hi>Old</hi> Coals, and kindling the <hi>Fire</hi> againſt another <hi>Day.</hi> And is this all that Viſitation upon Viſitation, Plague upon Plague, hath wrought upon us? Have we been <hi>Stricken,</hi> and do we <hi>revolt more and more;</hi> as if our Backs Itch'd for the Rod under which they ſmarted ſo lately? Is not the Fire ſtill in our Bones, and the Ruins of it yet viſible in our <hi>unrepared</hi> Fortunes? And do we <hi>Tempt</hi> God to ſmite us once more; and purſue his Vengeance through the <hi>ſame Tracks,</hi> wherein it formerly found us? It might have been hoped e're this, that our Faſt would have been the better half of a Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving; and the more ſeaſonable Duty of the Day, to <hi>bleſs</hi> and <hi>praiſe</hi> God for his Mercy, in the Rebuilding of our City; than
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51921:18"/> to <hi>weep</hi> before him that our Sins have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed it. But alas, we have neither <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated</hi> our Repentance, nor <hi>throughly</hi> reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered our Hurts. Our Schiſms are as <hi>many</hi> and <hi>wide;</hi> our Hearts as ready for Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as if we had hitherto ſin'd with Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and our City had never been <hi>deſtroyed</hi> at all. That we have no encouragement to rejoyce and keep Holy-day, ſo long as thoſe Sins Reign, that have been ſo fatally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky to us; and ſtill <hi>look big,</hi> and threaten us with another <hi>Storm.</hi> Our Faſts have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been ſo far from curing us of our Fears, that they are <hi>Dangerous,</hi> and a part of the Sins we <hi>wot</hi> of. <hi>We Faſt for Strife and Debate,</hi> (if not <hi>to ſmite with the Fiſt of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs.</hi>) And at that very Inſtant, when the occaſion ſummoneth us together, to Repent of our Schiſms, and pray for a peaceable and happy Union; we are <hi>then</hi> Schiſmatical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly divided; and keep <hi>up</hi> the Sin, while we pretend to <hi>Atone</hi> for it. That our Prayer and Faſting, and other external ſhews of Humiliation, inſtead of being <hi>Acts</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, are become the <hi>Subjects</hi> of it; and are as much to be lamented, as our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sins; Thus like an ill <hi>Craſis,</hi> we turn
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51921:19"/> the very <hi>Remedy</hi> into <hi>Humour</hi> and <hi>Diſeaſe.</hi> Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> tells us that Schiſm is a Sin,<note place="margin">Cyp. <hi>de unit Eccleſ.</hi>
               </note> which <hi>Martyrdom</hi> will not expiate: meaning, I ſuppoſe; the Martyrdom of ſuch as Die out of the Communion of the Church: much leſs then will Contrition and Tears a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, if they be <hi>Schiſmatical.</hi> For this is but to Repent, and Sin in a <hi>Circle;</hi> and when we have <hi>done</hi> the former, we are as much to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin</hi> as ever. That there's <hi>no</hi> reaſon there ſhould ever be an end of our Faſts, and as little Hopes that ever we ſhall Faſt to any <hi>Purpoſe;</hi> until we return to the <hi>Communion</hi> of the Church, and perform <hi>This</hi> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Acts of Religion, <hi>with one Mind and with one Mouth.</hi> For whatſoever Sin a Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent diſcharges himſelf off, by Duties of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, performed in any <hi>ſeperate</hi> Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; by the very ſame Act he puts ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the File, <hi>viz.</hi> an <hi>actual Schiſm,</hi> and ſo makes them up again both in Weight and Tale.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we have not yet recovered the <hi>Judgment</hi> of this Day. For though we dwell in our Gieled Houſes, yet the Houſes of the Lord lie waſt in many places; <hi>The</hi> Houſe of the Lord, <hi>The</hi> Temple of the Living God (in<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Pauls.</note>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:51921:19"/> compariſon whereof, all the reſt are but <hi>Tabernacles</hi> and <hi>Synagogues</hi>) is yet but an<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi>
               </note> Embryo: and the <hi>Adverſaries of</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Benjamin, the <hi>Babylonians</hi> abroad, and the <hi>Samaritans on this ſide the River,</hi> wiſh it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver may be otherwiſe. And what hinders the Progreſs of ſo Magnificent and Pious an Undertaking; but that <hi>the Hands of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe 4.</note> 
               <hi>of</hi> Judah, <hi>are weakened</hi> by our Factions and Diviſions? On one hand, it is ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that 'tis like to be but a neſt of <hi>Idolaters;</hi> and indeed our <hi>Schiſms,</hi> if any thing, are like to make it <hi>ſo.</hi> Others, that compare the Sins of the <hi>former,</hi> with thoſe of the <hi>preſent</hi> Age; fear, leaſt it ſhould rather be, a <hi>Den of Thieves</hi> again, or a Prey to the devouring Flames. But thus the Work, on all Hands, is diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged. A <hi>Work,</hi> that <hi>David</hi> would have been. <hi>Proud</hi> to have <hi>done;</hi> and it was not the leaſt of <hi>Solomon's Glories,</hi> that he <hi>did it.</hi> A <hi>Work</hi> which the Devout <hi>Jews</hi> equally affected with their <hi>Liberty,</hi> if not <hi>more:</hi> Laying the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, as Men <hi>Overjoy'd,</hi> with <hi>Trumpets</hi> ſounding, the <hi>People</hi> ſhouting, and the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 3. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſinging one of the Songs of Sion.</hi> The like <hi>Pious Zeal</hi> was eminent in the Ancient Church; for no ſooner were the Primitive
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51921:20"/> Chriſtians got looſe from their <hi>Slavery</hi> and<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſeb. <hi>Ecl. Hiſt.</hi> l. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Perſecution,</hi> and bleſs'd with a calm and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable <hi>Interval;</hi> but they endeavour'd to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Mercy, in <hi>Erecting</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating</hi> Places of Religious Worſhip, to the Honour of their Great <hi>Benefactor.</hi> And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, We cannot more <hi>aptly</hi> expreſs our <hi>Sence</hi> of the Divine Favour, in reſtoring our <hi>Houſes</hi> to <hi>themſelves,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> to our <hi>Houſes;</hi> than by Preparing a <hi>Dwelling</hi> for <hi>Him</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us: A <hi>Dwelling</hi> ſome way <hi>Proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> to the <hi>Mercy,</hi> in Rebuilding <hi>Ours</hi> ſo <hi>ſoon,</hi> and ſo much <hi>beyond Themſelves:</hi> and ſuitable in <hi>Magnificence</hi> and <hi>Splendour,</hi> to his Eſſential <hi>Grandeur</hi> and <hi>Majeſty.</hi> For from <hi>Hence, Solomon</hi> took his Meaſures, for the Building of the <hi>Temple,</hi> 2 Chron. 2. 5. <hi>The Houſe which I Build, is Great; for Great is our God above all Gods. This</hi> would be a good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our <hi>Repentance;</hi> and ſome ſmall Reſtitution, for our late <hi>Sequeſtration &amp; Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> the Effects of <hi>Schiſm &amp; Rebellion. This</hi> would <hi>Invite &amp; Confirm</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Glory of Gods Preſence among us. <hi>This</hi> might be a means to compoſe our <hi>Diviſions,</hi> and reduce <hi>ſober</hi> men to the Communion of the Church, by the <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> of her Service daily
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51921:20"/> perform'd therein. And, among other Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, why ſhould we not hope, that the Peace and Security of the <hi>Government,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wicked Endeavours of the <hi>Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>Rebellious,</hi> might be one? While the Prieſts of the Lord <hi>embody</hi> to lift up <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> Hands; and <hi>to offer Dayly Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. 1</note> 
               <hi>of ſweet Savor, and Pray for the Life of the King, and of his Sons,</hi> or Succeſſours.</p>
            <p>But, Alas, our <hi>ſins</hi> yet ſtand between <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> and ſo Great a <hi>Mercy;</hi> and I doubt, the <hi>Samaritans</hi> are no Friends to the <hi>Deſign.</hi> Do they not perſwade their <hi>Bigoted</hi> Saints, that God is more <hi>Purely &amp; Spiritually</hi> Worſhip'd in their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhallowed</hi> Synagogues? Do they not Greedily Spunge a <hi>Monopoly</hi> of all Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Charity to the <hi>Clan?</hi> Do they not, by ſtirring up <hi>Feuds</hi> and <hi>Commotions,</hi> put the State into ſuch <hi>dubious <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainties,</hi> that Pious Well-minded Men, whoſe <hi>Zeal</hi> is run down by their <hi>Fears,</hi> are Jealous of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Good</hi> leaſt their <hi>Charity</hi> ſhould be ſubject to a<note n="*" place="margin">17138 <hi>l. toward the Repairing</hi> Pauls, <hi>taken out of the Chamber of</hi> London, <hi>to carry on the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and the Materials Sold, to pay off the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears of</hi> Jephſon's <hi>Regiment.</hi> Heylin <hi>in the Life of</hi> Laud.</note> 
               <hi>late Abuſe,</hi> and turn to the <hi>Publick</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment? But I hope the <hi>Government</hi> will ſhortly Anſwer that <hi>Objection;</hi> And that we ſhall again ſee ſuch Happy Times when <hi>Piety</hi> will be no <hi>Scandal,</hi> when there will be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51921:21"/> no <hi>Danger</hi> in <hi>Doing Good.</hi> But how much more Happy would they be, if we would every Man (as it is our Duty) concur with the Government to make them ſo! If we would <hi>Repent</hi> of our <hi>Schiſm, Sedition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion;</hi> If we would <hi>Repent</hi> and <hi>leave</hi> them, and let God &amp; his Church, the King &amp; his Government, never hear <hi>more</hi> of them. Then ſhould ſoon we ſee the <hi>Temple</hi> in its Glory, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in her pefect Beauty, &amp; <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in Peace: Then ſhould we ſee the Church and State and City, deliverd of their <hi>Grievances</hi> and <hi>Fears,</hi> and Eſtabliſh'd in the Way of a <hi>laſting Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</hi> In Order whereunto, let us endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to <hi>Live Peaceable</hi> and <hi>Quiet Lives,</hi> in all <hi>Godlineſs and Honeſty.</hi> Let us put away all <hi>Bitterneſs,</hi> and <hi>Wrath</hi> and <hi>Clamour,</hi> and <hi>Evil-ſpeaking,</hi> and all <hi>Malice.</hi> Let us <hi>Study</hi> to be Quiet, to be of <hi>One Mind,</hi> and to <hi>Live in Peace,</hi> and <hi>the God of Peace ſhall be with us.</hi> Yea <hi>the Lord ſhall ſo Bleſs us out of</hi> Sion, <hi>that we ſhall ſee</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>in Proſperity all our Lives long.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Peace be within her Walls, and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity within her Palaces, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51921:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
